[Music]
so this is kind of a new experiment I'm
going to do a three-way conversation Tim
you want to introduce yourself a little
bit what what do you do and what are
your interests I'm a curious human being
first and foremost and that has led me
to write a huge number of books 35 I
think now exploring the different
spiritual traditions of the world really
looking for their commonality where they
where underneath the difference they
seem to be addressing a common human
experience of what could be called
awakening and that then led me to write
what became a international bestseller
so that kind of changed my journey on
Gnosticism the jesus mysteries and then
choosing the lost goddess and then the
last 20 years since then really has been
about trying to integrate this my own
experience of the world this spiritual
wisdom and the modern culture of
scientific understanding into one
philosophical understanding and then to
put that aside something which can give
people the actual experience of
awakening now so it's not only an idea
it's an experience there's a few things
that you talked about and it you've
written about that are now getting a lot
more attention it seems there's a kind
of weave the whole idea of rebel with
rebel wisdom is that we are trying to
kind of understand explain and
contextualize what seems to be quite a
big intellectual awakening that's going
on online the whole manifestation of
long-form content long-form YouTube
videos has led to what a lot of people
are kind of recognized as a real desire
for knowledge and a kind of an
intellectual awakening and part of that
clearly is the sort of jordan peterson
phenomena the intellectual dark web
phenomena and tied in to that it's a new
interest in christianity new interested
in Gnosticism and as well there is with
Jordan Peterson's kind of reframing of
the of the Christian story in
Psychological turn
and there's a real there's a real
interest in the religious and the sacred
again after a long time of the kind of
new atheist types like Richard Dawkins
and sam Harris of kind of they felt to
me like they had a bit of a stranglehold
on the culture this sort of radical
scientific skepticism so how does it
feel to you what do you make of that
chorale I mean look I have a I had a lot
of time for Richard Dawkins and people
like that because I think what they were
doing is they were still fighting the
Enlightenment battle which everyone what
I thought they've been one turned out it
haven't been one so the thing which they
are attacking needs attacking however
the side effect of it is you've just
said though is is this idea that it you
can't be intellectually credible and
interested in the depths of ancient
wisdom or the depths of your own natures
salt this is these are even to use that
word is immediately you're no longer
intellectually credible so I'm really
really really pleased to see a renewed
interest in depth and my whole hope is
that we can develop I want to get it to
the place where people couldn't stand up
and say things which sat which which are
things like look I actually think that
death is not the end of this experience
I'm having a psychic I don't and I want
to be able to say that and not sound
like a woo idiot who's just bought into
a lot of superstitious myths and at but
actually has got something to say for
instance and I think we can move in that
direction I want to see a rational the
science you know in general terms came
in that whole movement in hit in history
to question and replace irrational
religion now we want the other end of
that dialectic is to replace it with
rational spirituality and if what's
happening now with greater nuance and
depth and long-form discussions can lead
to that I think that's that's the next
evolutionary step so this is an
interesting term for kind of rational
spirituality
how does that differ to an irrational
spirituality what are the key
differences for you well first of all
I'm not against a little bit of
irrationality I mean I'm I'm I I love to
step out into what not knowing which is
not irrational but irrational not
knowing for me is the foundation of
everything so the place we have to start
and finish is oh my god what you know
this is we're in a breathtaking mystery
that we exist and the more we find out
about it the more profoundly mysterious
it becomes so there's that humility is
the place to start I don't know like
being alive now for almost 60 years I've
never met anyone who knows I'm guessing
that nobody knows I don't even know what
it would mean to know actually what that
would mean so there's this enormous
breathtaking mystery and then we do our
best to understand it and we need to be
open to everything and diet is our
greatest ally on that so that what's
wrong with irrational spirituality is it
doesn't have the doubt it doesn't move
on it's based on a reverence for old
ideas which should become established
written in old books
it doesn't question itself and therefore
it's stuck and there and people who
believe it if they don't question them
they're doing it unconsciously which is
why most people are doing it with
something to happen to be born in what
rationality does is from impression
ality all it means is having a good
reason so if you think it's in the Bible
is a good reason then that's a good
reason I don't think that's a good
reason but what's really interesting as
well as the idea so the Bible the books
in the Bible were assembled over many
centuries millennia and it sounds like a
great idea
so take the best wisdom that you've got
and make that into a way of living your
life but at some point someone says okay
right we're done this is it the Bible is
finished no one's ever going to come up
with any other new ideas that need to be
in this book and that that for me sounds
peculiar but when you understand the
Bible's accreted over many years it
sounds like well that would there's a
lot of there's got to be a lot of
accumulated wisdom in there but at what
point do you say right nothing more we
need to know we just need to live by
these rules exactly and and the whole
I mean you know obviously you you're
aware of the beautifully circular kind
of literalist view of the Bible where
it's like I know it's true because it's
in the Bible how do you know it's true
because the Bible says the Bible is true
and you've just going boom boom boom
round in a circle so and that has to be
a historical you the whole collapse of
the literalist view of Christianity came
through Protestant Reformation leading
to the study of the Bible which no one
had done and then you have an historical
appreciation of it and then it's no
longer the revealed Word of God and then
it's up for question and then you start
learning the history of it and it's not
great history and the people that have
been involved in it are not the sort of
people that you want to trust I talked
before about this kind of intellectual
awakening that a lot of people are kind
of recognizing is this something that
you've encountered do you feel that
you've been stimulated by stuff you've
been seeing online recently well I was
stimulated by the documentary you made
with Jordan Peterson I mean that that's
been the most obvious example for me
where there's been this phenomena happen
and my entry point from was somebody
sending me videos but the first one was
the one you made which I thought was
excellent and I saw that this was deeply
questioning seeing again seeing Jordan
on the news was astonishing for me half
an hour with an intellectual being
questioned was wow this doesn't happen I
mean I can't think of a phenomena like
it may be Bertrand Russell in my
lifetime I mean just about in my
lifetime but not since it and so Sam
Harris of course and all that so there
is a definite I like most people when I
came to communicate my ideas for people
in the know are telling me all you need
to make it short snappy sound by it's
simple and I'm quite out for simple as
long as it's not too simple it's not
simplistic it's like carbines die sets
very famously or even as simple as
possible but no simpler and that's a
good mantra but actually turns out
people who want
want depth so that I'm finding people
are responding to a real conversation
which is what I've loved always that's
why I spent my life doing so that
suddenly there's a chance to have real
conversation with people like yourself
and there's a lot of people who are
going oh yes please I think that's just
really significant I mean how wide that
spreads we'll see but that the John
Peterson effect has been so out of the
blue really I I'm gonna admire you for
seeing it coming because I certainly
don't see it coming yeah it's
interesting we were sort of very we want
to make sure that our channel is not
just kind of Jordan Peterson only but
it's such a useful window and lens to
start looking at what's going on in the
culture and obviously the expansion into
the intellectual dark web and other
people riding the same wave that Jordan
Peterson talks about and I know that you
you've written quite a lot of
agnosticism in the past one of the
things that got us quite a lot of
pushback was in that first child release
and documentary we mentioned Gnosticism
and a lot of people didn't like that do
you what can you explain what Gnosticism
is firstly and why it's always been like
this controversial thing within
Christianity so Gnosticism is a general
term for a whole wide range of sex in
the ancient world who were very very
different actually what linked them
together was that their idea of
Christianity was based around the
experience of new gnosis which is
knowing deep mystical knowing knowing of
oneself and knowing of God which turns
out to be the same thing so that so
they're they're about knowledge whereas
traditional literalist Roman
Christianity which is what we're really
talking about the the religion of the
Roman Empire is about belief pissed as'
notice and pestis so they are they are
rivals in the first centuries for the
soul of Christianity the version taught
by the Roman Empire which has been
embraced pretty much unquestioned until
recently is that the Gnostics were
heretics who kind of went pagan and got
confused and are therefore dangerous and
will lead you astray the truth in my own
opinion from my own studies is the
opposite that the Gnostics are the
original Christians who were then
literalized into a cult which became
part of the Roman Empire and then
destroyed everything the pagan world the
Jewish world indeed as well and ancient
Gnosticism and there's always been this
battle in between this established
religion of an empire and this rebel
undercurrent which is about not priests
and bishops but you knowing for yourself
through a direct experience of gnosis
and we we both worked on this particular
line in the documentary but we kind of
suggested that he he had a gnostic the
jordan Peterson had a more Gnostic
understanding Christianity and a lot of
people really push back on that they
really didn't like yeah I mean why why
Jordan has got a more Gnostic
appreciation of it from what I
understand of him is that he's a myth
mythologies that the thing which marks
out the Gnostic Christians is that they
are looking at the Jesus story and
indeed the other stories but the Jesus
story as an as a spiritual allegory
which leads to gnosis it's not about a
belief in an actual historical event
about a real man it's that rather he is
an everyman character as young of course
himself was a gnostic and wrote the
seven servants of the dead in the name
of a gnostic teacher bazzill a des and
bought the gnostic manuscripts once so
which is why we have them is the that
Jesus is an archetype of the self so
that they were seeing the Jesus story
right from the birth and the cave to the
empty cave at the end as an allegory
about one's own spiritual journey
through stages of initiation to this
awakening that's not what I was told at
Sunday School and because of that
mismatch that's why people are very wary
of the Gnostics and something I've
always found fascinating it a bit
confusing talking to two Christian
friends is that they often say that it
is the literal physical resurrect
of Jesus that is at the core of at least
that form of literalist Christianity and
without him the whole thing kind of
falls apart why is that yeah why is that
it's big there you know the strange
thing is you know that only makes sense
if you have a literal atom and even than
a literal fall because the whole
mythology is that it's a it's redemption
for that fall so if you really go down
the literalist road and you're willing
to believe that everything was created
in seven days and Adam and Eve and all
the rest of it then you do need a
literal Jesus but if you understand that
as mythology then you can understand
Jesus as mythology it's just a big jump
people feel they're losing something you
know if when they read my you know or
come across my ideas and it's like oh
you don't you think that Jesus is a myth
it's like oh the the truth however is
the opposite what strikes me is that
everyone has their own Jesus you know
you speak to a fundamentalist and Jesus
is a you know fire and brimstone you
talk to a nice Quaker and Jesus is a
passive this you talk to Muslim and
Jesus is a prophet like Muhammad but
just not quite as good and the you know
or eise you know everyone's got their
own Jesus and he's just like them now if
there was an historical Jesus most
people must accept that their Jesus is
not the real one and that they're
they're having a relationship with a
fantasy which is Trembley sad on the
other hand if you understand that the
figure is designed to be a
representation for your own deeper self
it's exactly right you should have your
own Jesus I have my own Jesus Jesus is
in my life it's just not it's not a
literal man it's a it's a mask of God
like Joseph Campbell said so it's
something which you reach through just
in the same way that you know I don't
think most people certainly the West
would see there was a literal Krishna or
additional Vishnu or a middle drama that
in the same way or indeed the ancient
gods the Dionysus or Cyrus so do you
think Jesus really existed no no I think
the evidence personally really really
points us three there's three prongs to
that really I mean I certainly didn't
set out with that I mean I when I
started work on the Gnostics I
I assumed there was a real Jesus that
almost became a friar when I was younger
you know brought up in the Church of
England and very nearly joined the
church but eventually with the research
there seem to be three things one was
the incredible similarities between
ancient pagan mythology and what became
with Jesus story and seeing that in that
in these ancient pagan myths of a son of
god or a god man were all the motifs now
people attack that because there's no
there's no ancient story which is the
same it's not like a it's not just
copied but it's more like you would get
in film today or in you know if you took
I don't know the matrix you could
probably go look he's taken that from
there and that's come from there and
that's and from it's created a whole new
thing that's of the Jesus time it's just
taken all these motifs so that just
about every single thing probably
everything actually that makes up the
Jesus story as a narrative is already
there in the ancient world and so
there's that so it resembles pagan myths
there's the fact that the earliest
Christians don't deny this there you can
get Justin Martyr who actually it makes
a virtue of it that the similarities so
they're not the why it's a shock today
when people realize it's the same as
pagan mythology it wasn't then it was
obviously so that's the one kind of part
of it and then there the others are
Gnostics which is here is a group of
people who are predate actually the idea
of year 0 because there is no USERRA so
they've been around and they're studying
the myths of the the earth mythology and
and that as an allegory Exodus in
particular they're around Alexandria
where I think all of this is being
written which is like the New York of
the ancient world big Jewish community
all speaking Greek which is the English
of the ancient world and they are
writing all these documents in in Greek
and we have loads of them which accord
into testamental texts and they're a
combination of Jewish mythology and
pagan mythology and then at the end of
them becomes this other these other
texts these Gnostic texts which I think
are there all Gnostic which have this
amazing story of the
ridhima which are very similar to pagan
myths and they themselves are a mixture
of pagan and Jewish mythology and it
just feels us a natural continuation and
they see it as their great heresy for
which they were put down is Jesus never
came in the flesh he comes in you so
that's the two and then the third thing
is there is no evidence for historical
man none nothing absolutely nothing and
the only things which are held up but
this little passage in the Jewish
historian Josephus is I mean any any
scholar with this all know the fake is
that the language is wrong it's been
added later it's and it shows just how
they were desperate to find some
something which they could hang this
room so it's not important to me really
whether there was or wasn't a historical
Jesus then more and more interested in
what the myth means but I don't think
there was there was another part of that
myth my understanding which integrated
Sofia so kind of Divine Feminine
archetype which seems very missing from
Christianity otherwise so what was
Sophia to the Gnostics yeah isn't that
mean isn't that amazing there was a
Christian goddess I mean isn't that I
realized was so excited when we started
getting into that and as a philosopher
Philo so fear and lover of Sofia as my
alright cool so she gets called but she
got lots of names Sofia's just one the
pagan mythology I think has taken it
that comes into Christianity in that in
its original Gnostic form as a quitter
nity I think there is father and son
mother and daughter and they represent
in the mythology they the the the male
archetype is is a source the mystery the
unseen the that's God God is the source
of potentiality for everything and the
goddess is all form that the probably
the easiest understanding of that is
knew it in the Egyptian tradition the
night sky she's the whole universe and
everything within it that's the canopy
and through the karakia are holes the
stars where the light beyond which is
the male principle shines and then she's
so wearing her now she is all the forms
she is soul/psyche for and and then that
individuals so now there's the Sun which
is that potentiality that pure being
consciousness but he knew and in me so
that's our end and that's the son and
then the daughter is our soul
it's our particular fragment of the
world soul or the cosmic soul and so the
job of redemption so the Noah the
gnostic myth is one of the fall and so
Sofia which is everyone's soul man and
women falling into mater getting lost
looking for love looking from the light
and looking in all the wrong places
becoming abused and having a very hard
time lots of suffering and then turning
around and crawling back to her father
help me and then the male principle
sends the son to rescue her and he's her
brother
stroke lover as you're only allowed to
be in myths and comes down and and
that's the Jesus figure and in the Jesus
story
you get the two you get the Virgin Mary
at the mouth of the cave the the stable
but actually it's cave and the Greek so
she's at the mouth of the cave and she's
the goddess of Justice who brings that
she's on the left hand of the left hand
path which brings souls in and out of
incarnation Jesus is going to sit on the
right hand which leads people away from
that but she's recycling Souls and Jesus
comes in and he's the perfect initiate
goes through his life and then and then
and then part of that is the meeting the
other Mary who's the fallen woman has
Sofia I mean there's taken directly from
the Sofia myth and he takes out seven
demons well the place where people will
be most aware of those seven levels now
it's the Indian chakras but actually
it's also there in the in the pagan
mythology and and mithra isn't
particularly so he's taking her through
these different levels of purification
and then she what she she then becomes
the what she becomes Sofia she becomes
the wise woman and in in the Gnostic
literature after his death it is Mary
Magdalene who teaches the
prett teachings to the 12 disciples
because the 12 men are the the signs of
the zodiac so Jesus is the still point
in the middle and they dance around him
literally dance and when one of the
documents they dance around him and they
are the twelve signs of we're on the
wheel the wheel of suffering or in the
in the in the pagan version it's a wheel
of grief Pythagoras causes the wheel of
grief it's the same as the Indian thing
so we're stuck on the wheel and and she
reveals the wisdom to how to find the
center and so she's the dis she still by
the Catholic Church is still called the
disciple to the disciples
so quite important and really
interesting if you go back to the
Gnostic literature one of the great
things they're condemned for which is
really interesting is that the
pythagorean's release so they treat
women really well and and of there's a
guy called Celsus who writes about
attacking the Gnostics and every gospel
he mentions just about is accredited to
a woman and they're great you know they
have women priests and the church is
very upset about the whole thing but it
kind of interesting today from our point
of view to look back and go oh that's
much more like us why do you think this
is relevant or why do you think that why
is this important now I think for me
they're going back with Christianity
which is you know my early work 20 years
ago is a bit like psych therapy it's a
bit like our culturally we need to go
back there's a there's a schism in the
Western soul between our pagan roots and
our Christian roots and we've been told
that they're their enemies and they're
not they're exactly the same thing
Christianity is paganism there's just
one evolutionary current in the West of
course how could there be otherwise and
that and I think there's a great healing
that can happen with that and I also
think the return to the Gnostic spirit
which has been so prevalent since the
sixties there's a return to self that
the individual journey of the syph self
inquiry and do you think that's become
more popular because of the kind of
spiritual technologies we have that the
psychedelics in the internal experience
of the divine that a lot of people have
had
have led to a revival of Gnosticism wow
that's really it I mean certainly
psychedelics I think did play a big role
so many different currents also you know
we brought in a lot of the eastern
wisdom which had kept those currents
alive because they hadn't gone through
the same level of individuation that we
did they missed that but and they're
suffered for it but they benefit by
keeping that other current alive so it
looked very attractive to us so we could
go across to to a Asia and just go oh
you've got the inner mystery still and
then then that's what I did most of my
early books are on Eastern spirituality
and then looking at the Gnostics and
dynamic goddess it's right here in our
Western tradition and it heals that
divide so for me it's I'm more
interested in where how we take it
forward but I think there's something
very healing about it and there's
something which enables us to choose a
different path you know when when we
were at the Jesus mysteries so 99 was
the beginning of a lot of attacks on
religion and rightfully so in my view -
but our book is dedicated to the Christ
in you it's not coming from an atheistic
condemn it's all a waste of time
viewpoint it's going let's see it
differently and I think that's a that's
a much more healthy option than just
dismiss it we're now into science that's
all rubbish mythological mumbo jumbo
it's actually going no no no we need all
of it this is all part of the human
experience and it's a and it's or
there's a value in it
huge value actually can you talk a bit
more that's a really interesting
metaphor talking about sort of
psychotherapy for the split and the
Western soul can you explain more about
what that means and what it is that
we've split off from and what we need to
what the heat that healing looks like
yeah I think we set up we set up an
opposition a long time ago and then with
the triumph of lid using this maps on to
say in McGilchrist work about the left
brain and the right brain and
[Music]
because he because he argues that the
left brain has effectively been at war
with the right brain the left brain may
of being more particular being more
rational and the right brain having Anna
kind of more open to the oneness
experience and sort of the sense of
unity with all things and I I I really
admire Ian's work I think he's a
extraordinary man I'm not completely
sure about that version of history it
feels to me that we we didn't there
wasn't some place where we were all in
the oneness and open to that and then
the the rational left brain took over
and then we lost it I think that both of
always being present and and that the
ancient world doesn't look particularly
awake to me it looks full of suffering
and short brutal lives really unless you
happen to be an heiress to class in
which case it was you know and you could
sit around and do philosophy and so it
doesn't it doesn't feel like oh we had
it and then we lost it it to mean some
things we did but it to me it's more of
an evolutionary current where we had
that and then it particular eyes and and
something young talks about with
Christianity is it it's but there was
part of an individual process by kind of
narrowing it down this one man who saved
everything was in some way part of this
thing which happened in the West which
has led to us where we're compared to
our ancestors highly individuated very
particular where we don't you know we're
not all wearing the same things that
anymore we're not we there's variation
huge variation thinking in different
ways and and we've had that in a way
that didn't happen in the ancient world
and certainly then didn't happen to me
so much so that you see this break where
that starts to happen with the triumph
of Christianity and this monotheistic
hold it has on the Western world and
then the ancient soul comes back with
the Renaissance and you get the
discovery of the the ancient texts
Atika the the platonic texts and you see
the birth of this incredible awakening
very much like now I think this the
extraordinary awakening in the arts and
in the intelligence and in its in
scholarly studies in the past and it
starts what's going to become science so
that current coming back in now we we
can see how it that has all happened
then it feels like we can integrate we
it's going to help us integrate our past
and the whole point for doing that is to
go forward is to feel that we don't have
to get now stuck in this rather fallen
limited reductionist science where we've
ended up which is phenomenal on the one
hand I mean I've so much respect for its
achievements
it's unbelievable what it's done and
it's philosophically pretty impoverished
and is literally soul destroying
literally has taken this experience
we're having right now have the psyche
the soul and gone it's a kind of an
illusion created buying a piece of meat
and of no significance whatsoever
really and that reductionism is so
damaging to the heart to the soul so if
we can integrate all of that together
there maybe we can step forward into
something which goes look there's value
in all of that there's a there seems to
be another beautiful cycle there of when
things become unmovable in our culture
we look into the ancient past and a few
people who've spoken to you have said
exactly that
so what do you think is the weight or
what's your particular way of doing that
but there's a lot in the past and I
suppose
selecting what's needed for right now
selecting the right wisdom it's quite
important so what are some of the ways
you think we can start using ancient
wisdom to start moving forward in the
society you know what I mean I've been
embedded in it for so long so many
decades it's kind of it's just in me now
and so in my actual response to your
question is the danger I think now is
the opposite I what I see as
romanticization of the past and I
they're kind of a way of oh we had it
then and we lost it or the people who
are still living in the jungles they've
got
we haven't got and it just feels like
look there is something which we lose
you always lose something when you gain
something and there's something which
cultures that live in very different
ways have that we don't have that's for
sure
but I'm really really careful of this
romanticization of it as if somehow we
need to get back to something I don't
think we do I think we need to keep
going with the evolutionary current just
just we're doing we're doing fine you
know it's raising place quite
astonishing where we are and we're in
better shape than we've ever been and we
just need to keep going and integrate
the thing which is which is missing and
right now what is missing is well the
reductionist thing is the problem
because that takes everything and pulls
it down to the book the most basic level
and what excites me and my latest work
is this emergentist view that's arriving
with an evolutionary understanding which
says the opposite to reduction which
goes no don't reduce everything to its
components actually see that greater and
greater wholes are emerging greater than
there's creativity to the whole process
of the the universe so you've got that
literally in the construction of the
physical universe and the biological
universe and I think also the universe
of the soul which is what we're talking
about when we're talking about the
history of Western ideas so I find that
really interesting this idea of a model
of reality that is somehow inherently
evolutionary and it's always going to
some kind of greater whole could you
talk a little bit more about that and
what that means to you yeah I'll be
delighted to this is my real passion my
latest work which I think is my best in
a book called soul story it's really
trying to lay out an emergentist
spiritual philosophy and the basic the
basic thesis comes from my technique is
a philosopher's to look at the moment
because that's what I've got so what was
this what's this what's this so what I
see when I look at the moment is a flow
of experiences so what seems to be real
is time despite the people that
constantly tell
that it's an illusion I don't really
know what that means because what I see
is every moment is this flow of time so
I started looking at the flow of time
and it felt like ah it with what the
qualities that it has in it is that
every moment is a is realizing a new
potentiality like this one isn't and a
new and no two moments were ever the
same these are obvious things but I'm
fascinated by the obvious and that every
moment also contains within it
implicitly everything that's happened
before so it feels like that's
interesting so so that we have this idea
in English that the past passes but it
hasn't passed it's actually right here
it's the time actually doesn't pass the
past accumulates there's just more past
and more past and more past and it's all
present implicitly in the moment and
that each moment has this quality of
being a new realizing a new possibility
and containing everything that's been
before so that the moment is made of the
past coexisting with the possible and
that feels to me a description of the
fundamental nature of what reality is so
that what we're seeing 13.8 billion
years ago if the dates are right is the
start for our universe of a process of
the realization of potentiality and as
the past accumulates as there's more and
more of it there is a richness of
complexity which tends towards what we
call evolution and trends towards the
emergence of novelty so that there's a
that to use a lovely line which is from
Brian swim the evolutionary philosopher
who I love to bits and who said
something like you know what have we
learned we've learned that if you take
hydrogen and you wait long enough it
learns to sing opera which i think is
just spectacular because that's what
we've looked it's like you lis take
hydrogen and it will emerge eventually
as you and me and and what I see in that
and my attempt to integrate science was
with a spiritual tradition is to go look
well in this idea of evolution or over
by
with Darwin and Wallace and the whole
idea that ever this huge variety of life
came from one simple source for a
stunning idea that is I mean just wow I
mean and everything seems to point
towards that being right and then a
hundred years ago we got the idea that
Noah's wasn't just biology that had
evolved a whole of that the universe had
evolved I mean and that some that is a
mythos of such grandeur I mean this is
why I say we're on we're on track guys I
mean these these leaves ancient myths
just like yeah whatever I mean this is
big stuff now so we've got that we've
got this ten billion years of the
evolution of the physical cosmos then
you've got the three billion years of
the evolution of life and then right at
the end of that you've got the evolution
of psyche which is Greek for soul it's
what the the Gnostics book there's a
gnostic word and it means the soul and
what it's pointing to what they're
pointing to what the word refers to is
this experience you and I are having now
of a non-material reality and we're in E
right now our bodies are sitting here
Minds doing it say you know things
you're listening and nodding that's how
our bodies are doing and all the actions
in a non-material realm and all the
meaning isn't it is in that non material
realm in the physical realm there's a
monkey making funny noises but in the
non material realm we are sharing
meaning that's the latest thing so the
whole evolutionary process is gone from
basic matter to something not made of
matter made of images what the
reductionists do is they reduce
everything to what's come before until
really it's just atoms or even lower
than that what the emergent ists do is
they go no no no it's reality emerging
on evermore at deeper levels more
emergent levels so the soul the psyche
is not some byproduct of anything it's a
it's a level of reality well that's what
spirituality says you know if you I've
just been to speaking of a psychedelic
festival in Hungary you know it's like
what people are exploring there is salt
and you can go off into it and there's
it's huge
there's worlds out there it's what
shamanic exploration all the whole of
spirituality
about that world that droite for the
ancient Egyptians the imaginal realm of
the Sufis the Bihar dozy there's a
thousand names the astral plane there's
a it's a dimension so my thesis is look
what spirituality does is it sees that
it's pre-existent that's always been
there and we have fallen from it
that's the gnostic myth it's a bit very
pessimistic we fall in this in life life
is his awful thing which you've got
trapped in a body and if you can just be
spiritual enough you can get out and you
never have to come back because who
would want to come back to hear what the
emergentist thing says is no no no
actually life is a beautiful thing and
it's emerging on ever deeper and more
emergent levels and it's emerged as
finally this world of psyche a world of
the soul a world in which in my opinion
we can actually survive without the body
and which we can explore in great depth
through spiritual practices but not as
something which has always been there
which unfortunately through some cosmic
mess-up we fell out of but actually
something which is emerging in an
evolutionary current so there's three
phases of evolution it's a physical the
biological and then this soul phase and
then at the end of that I think in this
new phase is where you started David is
the idea that what's coming now is this
deeper awakening to this oneness with
the very source that we're waking up to
a fundamental oneness with where all
this is come from and that's a whole new
thing again it feels to me to be a
really good place to to end don't like
having really good wrap up yeah it's a
glad story yeah Tim thank you very much
it's been a pleasure
you